These people are lined up to hear the oral
argument in the first software patent case
to be brought before the Supreme Court
in almost 30 years
- Do you guys want to introduce yourselves
and spell your names?
- Yeah, uh, uh, Bernie Bilski. B - I - L - S - K - I
- Rand - R - A - N - D, Warsaw - W-A-R-S-A-W
- Could you guys tell us in a nutshell
what you've invent?
- The invention is a guaranteed energy bill,
which is like a budget bill without a true-up,-
-and it's a method of hedging both sides in the
transaction. So, behind giving consumers,-
-energy consumers are guaranteed energy bill.
There's a lot of mechanics.
And the mechanics involve financial transactions
between energy consumption,
or energy consumers, and the energy providers.
THESE MEN HOPE TO GAIN A PATENT ON
A BUSINESS METHOD OF HEDGING
COMMODITY RISK
And that's what the invention is in a nutshell.
It's a method of generating guaranteed bills-
-for consumers and, also, for protecting
energy company earnings.
The outcome of the case will have profound
implications for software
- The Bilski Case itself is someone applied for a
patent on a business method or software,-
-and patent office rejected it. And now this is
that person suing the patent office, saying-
-"You have to grant me that patent."
This case is about what does it mean to be
a patentable process.
And so, since software patents fall under the
category of processes, because they are not-
-the machine, and they're not a composition of
matter, which are some of the other categories-
-of things that are patentable. This case will
define what it means to be a patentable process.
- What about justice Roberts? He said, you know,
basically your patent involves people picking
up the phone and calling other people.
- It could be reduced to that level, as the certain acts
that are performed, but it's much more than that.
It has to do with selling commodity that effects
price to one party, selling to a different party
at a different fixed price,
identifying counter risk positions.
If you look at claim four in the patent, we have things
called claims which describes what the invention is, -
-there's a long mathematical formula in there, that
didn't exist in nature or anywhere in the literature,
that these very inventive folks come up with.
- Once upon a time math was not patentable.
And nowadays we can have someone -
-like Bilski coming in and saying: "You know,
I worked hard on this mathematical equation -"
"- and therefor I should have a patent on this
information processing method here."
- You mention in your claim that there's a very long
calculation shown there.
Do you think a strong calculation or good math
is a basis for a patent?
- It can be.
- The basic process of writing software is that you
take a broad algorithm of some sort, you know, -
-some means of doing something with abstract data,
and then you apply variable names.
- So for our first derivation let's start with a simple
matrix, a matrix of values.
And we'll find the mean of each column, mu one,
mu two, mu three.
And we're gonna define Y to be X minus
mu for each column.
Now if we have some other factor, X, we can take
X dot S and find the projection of X onto this space.
This is called the singular value decomposition (SVD).
Now, here's the trick. Here's the great part. Let's
say that this first row, X1, equals sexuality.
Let's say X2 equals "Do you own cats?"
And X3 equals, I dunno, affection.
Ok, so, now we'll also say that, let's take a factor
J1 equals Jane's responses on this survey.
Let's say J2 equals Joe's responses.
Now let's do the same projections as we did before.
We're gonna take J1 dot S subtract J2 dot S.
We're gonna find the distance between these two
points, and we're gonna call that compatibility.
And in that simple step, we've derived patent
number 6 735 568.
The trick of our derivation was that before with
the SVD, we had abstract numbers.
What the guys at eHarmony did to get this patent,
was to assign names to our variables.
So instead of an abstract X1 we have sexuality,
instead of X2 we have a preference for cats.
And by making those assignments, by
setting variable names in this matter, -
-they were able to take an abstract concept
and turn it into a patentable device.
- What we want to do according to the heads of
our patent institutions, is take mathematics and
slice it up into as many slices as possible, and hand
those slices out. And, say, if you do a
principle component analysis, if you multiply matrices
for dating sites, we'll give that to eHarmony.
If it's for equities we'll give that to State Street. And
so on and so forth.
And what we're giving out is basically
exclusive rights to use mathematics, -
-to use a law of nature, in whatever context.
And what we get in return is basically nothing.
- The patents is a government grant, in the US it
arises out of the constitution.
- The Framers included the provision for granting
exclusive rights to inventors in our constitution,
and the belief was that that was important in order
to reward people who had made technological -
- advances that would benefit society.
- The rights that they are granted are not the rights
to do the things that they invent, -
-but the right to exclude others from doing
that thing.
- So the idea was you have a machine or a thing,
which is not previously described in any literature, -
-and which no skilled mechanic could figure out
how to make given what is described in literature, -
-and for that you get a patent.
- The basis for determining what is patentable
subject matter has continued to evolve -
- over the last 200 years of our national existence.
- In 1953 the Patent Act was modified by Congress,
to add the words "or processes" to the word -
- "product" in describing what could be patented.
The Congress which did that was plainly thinking of
processes of industrial manufacture. Processes -
- that produced something at the other end. Float
glass on molten tin, and it'll become flat, or whatever.
- And it's unlikely that anybody thought of process
at that time in terms of computer software, -
-because we didn't have applications on computer
software for many years after that last revision -
- of the Patent Act.
- Back in the late 70s the patent law was interpreted
such that you couldn't patent software. It was -
- considered a mathematical algorithm,
a law of nature.
The legal world changed. The environment was
quite different starting with some decisions by-
- the Supreme Court, like Diamond v. Diehr.
- The patent applicant was coming in with a new
process for curing rubber. The temperature, and-
- the preciseness of the temperature is essentials
in curing rubber well. And the innovation -
-that was being patented in this case was an
algorithm to monitor a thermometer -
- that was basically in the process and determined
when the rubber needs to be released and cooled.
- And they said "Processes for curing rubber are
patentable, there's nothing new about that, -"
"- the fact that they use a computer in implementing
it shouldn't change anything."
- The Supreme Court makes it clear that you can't
patent software, because it's only a set of -
- instructions, or an algorithm. Abstract laws of nature,
algorithms, are unpatentable in the US itself.
However, then there was the creation of the
Court of Appeals of the Federal Circuit.
- The problem being solved, in some sense, begins
with the fact that trial court judges always -
- hate patent cases.
And the reason they hate patent cases is, for a single
trial judge, a lawyer who has spent his/her life-
-doing litigation, a patent case in which she/he is going
to be required to find detailed facts about how paint is-
-made or how computers work or how radio broadcast-
ing operates, is an opportunity just to made into a fool.
- Congress is attempting to change the system in which
patent cases are litigated.
But instead of changing who tried patent cases,
Congress left a non-specialist district judge-
-in charge of the trial. And then created a new court of
appeals called the Federal Circuit,-
-who's job it was to hear all appeals from patent cases.
Rapidly, of course, this court filled up with
patent lawyers.
And the patent lawyers then made the law in the court
of appeals that applied to all those district judges-
-who were still making non-specialist decisions of
which they were afraid.
Naturally the Federal Circuit turned out to be a place
which loved patents.
And it's chief judge, Giles Rich, who lived to be very
very old and died in his late 90s,-
-was a man who particularly loved patents on
everything.
The Federal Circuit court under Giles Rich sort of broke
Diamond against Diehr lose from it's original meaning,-
-and came to the conclusion that software itself
could be patented.
- The Supreme Court basically left everything to
this court to decide.
- The PTO actually used to reject patents on software,
like in the early 1990s, and they did not allowed them.
And the applicants would appeal those
rejections to the Federal Circuit.
- In the world of machines you show the Patent Office
the machine,-
-and you've got a Patent Office who's claims were
"I claim this machine."
In the world of computer software there was no way
of defining what the unit was.
I don't claim a program, I claim a technique that any
number of programs doing any number of things could-
-possibly use. The consequence of which is very rapidly
we began to build up as real estate that somebody-
-owned and could exclude other people from a whole
lot of basic techniques in computer programming.
- What happened was, starting in the mid-90s, the
number of patents on software started soaring.
An industry attitude started changing too.
So you had Microsoft, which originally didn't deal
with software patents very much at all,-
-I guess they got sued in the early 90s
by Stac and lost a, uh,-
-significant judgment against them,
they started patenting.
- They're gonna have their own set of patents.
So that if a major patent holder threatens them,
they can fire back.
- Gradually companies like Oracle were forced to set
up patent departments just for defensive reasons.
They had to patent their stuff so that they had some-
thing to trade with the companies that had patents.
Mark Webbink:
- And so the arsenal started to develop. By year 2001
Microsoft now holds thousands of software patents.
Oracle was probably approaching a thousand software
patents. Adobe...
James Bessen:
- All of them become more and more aggressive.
Patenters and some of the ones who were against-
-software patents ended up suing other companies,
and so what you had is an explosion of patenting first-
-and then an explosion of litigation.
By the late 90s about a quarter of all patents
granted were software patents.
About a third of all litigation, patent litigation,
involves software patents.
About 40% of the cost of litigation is
attributable to software patents.
And those numbers have been going up.
So Charles Freeny invented a kiosk that goes in retail
stores, and the idea is you'd come in,-
-you could select the music selection, swipe your
credit card, put in a blank 9 track tape,-
-and this is is how long ago this patent was, and it
would write that music selection onto the tape-
-and you could go away with it.
The patent was drafted in a very vague language so
there were terms like "point of sale location",-
-and "information manufacturing machine".
And Freeny eventually sold this patent to somebody
who wanted to interpret those terms very broadly.
To basically cover e-commerce.
So here was this very limited invention for this kiosk,
and he wanted to interpret those terms in such a-
-broad way so that it would cover transactions that
took place over the Internet,-
-you could make them in your office, in your
bedroom, in your house, anywhere.
And so it covered virtually all of e-commerce.
The courts initially didn't agree with that interpretation
but they appealed it, and the appellant court largely-
agreed with them, and they were able to extract some
settlements out of well over a hundred companies.
But the significant thing is, here is this patent you
can't tell what it's boundaries were until you get to-
-the appellant court. What most people thought
it's boundaries were turned out to be wrong.
- One of the key properties of programming languages
is they're very very precise.
You can look at any program language in any language,
in C, Python, any language like this,-
-and you know exactly what it's doing. You can look
at two pieces of service code and you can say-
"Are this doing the same thing or different things?"
And we do this because computers are very picky-
-and we need to tell the computer exactly what we
need to do in order to accomplish some task.
The language patent lawyers use is almost the opposite.
There's an advantage in being vague, and being broad,
being non-specific, because the broader your language-
-the more things you, sort of, catch in your net.
- So it is a large problem in our patent system just
defining simply what is the context or the borders-
-of the patent. And what does it cover,
and what does it not cover.
And that ambiguity causes a lot of chilling effects,
because people are going to avoid doing anything-
-that could possibly be covered by the patent, even if in
reality the patent wouldn't cover what they wanna do.
- Let's imagine that in the 1700s the governments of
Europe had decided to promote the progress of-
-symphonic music, or as they thought, promote it.
Will a system of musical idea patents, meaning-
-anybody who could describe a new musical idea in
words could get a patent which would be a monopoly-
-on that idea and then he could sue anybody else
that implemented that idea in a piece of music.
So a rhythmic pattern could be patented, or a sequence
of chords, or a set of instruments to use together,-
-or any idea you could describe in words. Now imagine
it's 1800 and you're Beethoven, and you want to write-
-a symphony. You're gonna find it's harder to write a
symphony that you won't get sued for, than write-
-a symphony that sounds good. Because to write a
symphony and not get sued you're gonna have to-
-tread your way around thousands of
musical idea patents.
And if you complained about this, saying it's getting in
the way of your creativity, the patent holders would-
-say "Oh, Beethoven you're just jealous because we
had these ideas before you."
"Why should you steal our ideas?"
- People have been making music for thousands of
years. There were never any need for patents in-
-the field of music. And since the computer industry
has made programming possible, people have been-
-developing software as well, since right from its
beginning, there was never a need to have patents-
-in this field in order for the activity to happen.
- Almost everything we were doing back before 1980,
1981, in those things, patent played no role in it.
Cut & paste, the embedded ruler in a word processing,
word wrapping, a lot of the things that are real-
-important and we take for granted, and that are much
more innovative in many ways than patents we have-
-today, 'cos patents can be on some very minute
things, that's the way the law works.
Those things happened, we had great
advances without patents.
- One of the world's most respected computer scientists,
Donald Knuth, has said that if software patents had
been available in the 1960s and 70s when he was-
-doing his work, that it's probably the case that
computer science wouldn't be where it is today.
There would be blockades on innovation that could've
seriously prevented the kinds of technical solutions-
-that we take for granted today.
- The programmer writing a long program might
conceivably need to check whether 500 or-
-thousand different techniques are patented, and there
is no way that she possibly could.
- The Patent Office issues hundreds of software patents
all the time. Every Tuesday they issue 3,500 patents-
-and a large number of those relate to software. It's
just impossible to review all those patents every week-
-to make sure you're not doing something that could
infringe them.
- So there's a provision in the US patent laws that
basically holds patent infringers, ahem, at I guess-
-a greater liability if they are shown to willfully
infringe. So basically the idea is that if you knew-
-about a patent and you infringed on it, you should
have a stricter penalty than if you didn't know about it.
But what this results in is a situation where there is a
real disincentive to follow what patent has been made-
-and what new inventions there has been through the
patent system, because if you read every patent or-
-there's evidence to show that you have read patents,
then you are liable for willful infringement, you knew-
-about the patent and you infringed it anyway, and the
penalty is triple damages.
- A number of people suggested that software
should be removed from the-
-scope of patentability. Can you comment on that?
- Yes, well, I obviously disagree with that. And I don't
believe that software should ever be removed.
It's one of our greatest sources of technical innovation
in this country. And to come up with a test that would-
-somehow eliminate software would,
I think, be a disaster for the economy.
WOULD IT THOUGH?
- Mike and I estimate that outside of pharmaceuticals
and chemicals the patents, sort of, are acting like-
-10 or 20 percent tax. You know, the small developer
developing something, down the road he has to pay-
-that tax. And every small company I know in software,
as long as they've been around a few years and hit-
-the market, somebody is asserting a patent against
them, they're running into some potential difficulties.
They very frequently feel obligated to get patent
themselves for defensive purposes.
So all of that activity is a tax. It's not something that's
helping them innovate, it's an unnecessary activity.
- The primary thing we do is an issue tracking system
called RT, or Request Tracker, so it's customer service,-
-help desk, bug tracking, network operations, anything
where you've got a whole bunch of tasks that need to-
-get kept track of. And you need to know what
happened, what didn't happen, who did it,-
-who didn't do it, when. It's kind of a to do list on
steroids designed for a whole organization.
Pretty much everything is open source or free software,
under one license or another.
We'll get consulting customers or support costumers
who add indemnification language to our standard-
-contract or need us to sign theirs. And it says, in the
standard legalese, it's gonna say something like-
-we indemnify and hold them harmless and agree to
pay their legal fees and sacrifice our first-born, if-
-something happens and someone discover that our
software is violating a somebody else's patent.
It's very very rarely the case that we end up signing
something that has that kind of language in it.
But it eats up a lot of legal fees.
- Look at the innovative people in software in ICT,
and ask "Would they be better of if the patent system-
-was abolished?" The answer is probable "Yes".
- Who's benefiting? Patent lawyers is number one.
Number two, you've a small number of so called-
-trolls who are benefiting, but it's not clear even most
of them is making much money.
You're seeing more recently, in the last 4 or 5 years,
companies like Intellectual Ventures and-
-hedge fonds who are acquiring large volumes of these
trash patents and using them to extract hundreds-
-of millions of dollars from companies. They're
benefiting, they maybe the biggest beneficiaries.
- There's a lot of bad press in the last few years
about the harm that's caused by software patents.
And we think that's had a political influence on the PTO
to get them to slow down their issuance and start-
-rejecting them, and that's what has
resulted in the Bilski case.
- Well the biggest, first bad press story was the
Blackberry patents, where all the Congressional-
-representatives have their Blackberrys and there was
a company called NTP that sued the manufacture of-
-Blackberry saying that all Blackberrys infringed it's
patent. Well, NTP was this company which is just a-
-one person holding company, they didn't make any
products or services themselves, and so-
-this got a lot of attention in the Wall street Journal and
Washington Post, and Congress persons were really-
-upset that they may lose their Blackberrys and they
may not be able to communicate efficiently.
So that caused a lot of attention, then you had all these
patents on banking methods and imaging for checks,-
-those patent holders were asserting against the
banking industry, and the banking industry has-
-a lot of influence on Capitol Hill, and so they've been
going down there and saying "Look, these types of-
-patents are causing us lots of harm." Then you add
into that the whole patent troll phenomenon in-
-Eastern District of Texas, with small patent holders
suing large IT companies like Google, Microsoft-
-IBM and Hewlett Packard. And all these companies
also have legislative influence, and they've said-
-"These types of patents are causing real harm to our
business, they're costing us jobs, they're increasing-
-the price of products and services that we offer to our
customers, and you need to do something about it."
- The situation we find ourselves in is that the lower
court, the Court of Appeals of the Federal Circuit,-
-is essentially a court for patents,
for hearing patent cases.
And this is the first time the Supreme Court has
taken up that scope of patentability.
And specifically this test that was implemented by
lower court, does talk to software patents.
And so, it's basically a 20 year history of software
patents being granted due to the lower court.
And so, we're hoping that the Supreme Court will
clear up the mess that the lower courts created.
And restamp it's authority which basically said that
you cannot have software patents.
- When you saw the arguments that where brought
by Bilski's lawyer, the patent bar is in some sense-
-an organized lobby. And an expansive subject matter
that's available to be patented is in their interest.
And it's clear that that was frustrating to some of the
justices. Some of them were frustrated by how-
-expansive patentable subject matter has become.
- They seem somewhat dismissive of the idea that
you could patent this particular idea.
- I think people has a hard time getting over the idea
that you can get a patent on hedging commodity-
-risk. But if you actually look at the claims and look
at what's in there, it is a process and it's no-
-different than any other process. It just may be
that it's not the way that they thought of patent-
-law in the past.
- We were encouraged by the comments by the
justices which showed that they were skeptical-
-and which suggested that they understood that
software is little more than a series of steps,-
-that could be written out as mathematical formula,
or written out on a piece of paper, or, as was-
-mentioned by one of the justices,
typed out on a typewriter.
- Software patents on a general purpose computer
have never been explicitly endorsed by this court.
And this court has also shown no compunction about
reversing rules that've held for a very a long time.
They clearly thought that the petitioners here was
trying to get a patent on something very basic,-
-some basic forms of human activity.
MORE THAN 200,000 SOFTWARE PATENTS
HAVE BEEN GRANTED IN THE U.S.
PROGRAMMERS FIND IT INCREASINGLY DIFFICULT
TO WRITE SOFTWARE THEY WON'T BE LIABLE
TO BE SUED FOR
NOW IMAGINE...
Transcript version 2.2 by Martin Karlsson.
Licensed under CC-BY 3.0